https://policy.ku.edu/provost/privacy-policy

Skip to main content
Office of Provost and Executive Vice Chancellor Policy
Privacy Policy, General
PolicyPurpose: To set forth requirements regarding information entrusted to the University by the public and members of the KU community.
Applies to: All units in their handling of data, information and records in any form (paper, digital text, images, audio, video, microfilm, etc.) created, collected, accessed, used, handled, stored, managed or disposed of during the course of conducting University business (administrative, financial, instruction, research or service).
Campus: LawrenceEdwardsParsonsJuniper GardensYoderSalinaTopekaPolicy Statement: KU Commitment to Privacy
The University of Kansas is committed to safeguarding all Private Information entrusted to the University by the public and members of the KU community. This notice describes the University’s general privacy policy as it relates to the collection, protection and disclosure of such information. (Note: see the “Definitions” section below for the definition of “Private Information.”)
Collection and Protection of Information
Information may be collected in a variety of ways, paper or electronic, including but not limited to, Web sites, surveys, email, information requests, databases, etc., as required to support University activities.
Information collected, regardless of the method of collection or format, may be used only to carry out the authorized business of the University. The University shall make reasonable efforts to limit the Private Information it collects to only that information strictly relevant to accomplish a clearly defined institutional purpose.
Every unit is responsible for maintaining the necessary confidentiality, integrity and availability of the information it handles. Every unit is responsible for granting to assigned individuals within the unit the reasonable, minimum access to Private Information needed to accomplish the necessary institutional purposes. All University employees are required to abide by state and federal laws and University policies, procedures and guidelines regarding the handling and protection of Private Information.
Employees who become aware of a breach of the privacy or security of Private Information must report such breach immediately to the Information Services Customer Service Center at 864-8080. The Information Services Customer Service Center will notify the Office of the General Counsel and/or the KU IT Security Officer as required by the particular incident.
Additional University policies, procedures and guidelines apply to specific types of information. Further, individuals for whom the University collects, maintains, or processes their personal data are directed to review the supplementary Privacy Notice, provided here in accordance with European Union General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) available at this link: https://policy.ku.edu/general-counsel/data-protection-privacy-notice
Disclosure of Information
Private Information may be disclosed only to the extent that is permitted or required by law. Disclosure must comply with applicable requirements regarding consent or authorization for disclosure.
Legally Mandated Disclosure of Information
The University may be required to release information, including Private Information, where required by state or federal law or upon receipt of a subpoena, search warrant or other court order.
KU Employee Privacy When Using University Resources
The University supports a climate of trust and respect. The University does not ordinarily read, monitor or screen employees’ routine use of information resources, except as necessary to maintain quality of service, to investigate a breach of security or misuse of University information resources or where required by law.
For additional information about the appropriate use of University resources, refer to the Acceptable Use Policy.
Consequences: Violations of this policy may result in disciplinary action, up to and including dismissal of employees. Employment actions will be conducted under the advice and guidance of Human Resource Management and the Office of the General Counsel.
Contact: Information Services Customer Service Center
1001 Sunnyside Ave.
Lawrence, KS 66045
785-864-8080
itcsc@ku.edu
The Office of the General Counsel
245 Strong Hall
1450 Jayhawk Blvd.
Lawrence, KS 66045
785-864-3276
gencoun@ku.edu
KU IT Security Officer
1001 Sunnyside Ave.
Lawrence, KS 66045
785-864-9003
itsec@ku.edu
Approved by: Provost and Executive Vice ChancellorApproved on: Tuesday, October 30, 2007Effective on: Tuesday, October 30, 2007Review Cycle: Annual (As Needed)Related statutes, regulations, and/or policies: Student Records Policy
Information Technology Security Policy
Data Classification and Handling Policy
Data Classification and Handling Procedures Guide
Electronic Data Disposal Policy
Electronic Data Disposal Procedure
Internet-Based Credit Card Processing Policy
Password Policy
Acceptable Use of Electronic Information Resources
Procedures for Investigative Contact by Law Enforcement
Electronic Mail (Email) Policy
Gramm-Leach-Bliley Student Financial Information Security Program
Related Other: Laws:
Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) and related guidance
Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) and HIPAA Fact Sheet
Gramm-Leach-Bliley Financial Services Modernization Act (GLB)
Electronic Communications Privacy Act (ECPA)
PATRIOT Act and the Department of Justice Highlights of the USA PATRIOT Act
Computer Fraud & Abuse Act
Kansas Open Records Act
Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) and Information and Technical Assistance on ADA
European Union General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)
Definitions:
Private Information: includes all information protected by state and/or federal law or that the University is contractually obligated to protect. Private Information also includes information designated by the University as private (confidential or sensitive) through the creation of standards, procedures and guidelines. Access to these data must be tightly monitored.
Examples of Private Information include, but are not limited to the following:
Nondirectory student records as defined by FERPA and the University Student Records Policy
Financial aid and scholarship records
Individually identifiable personnel records.
Personal information utilized to verify identity, including but not limited to Social Security numbers (SSN) and University ID numbers (KU ID)
Passwords and PINS
Digital signatures
Individually identifiable health information protected by state or federal law (including but not limited to “protected health information” as defined by the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA).
Individually identifiable information created and collected by research projects.
Credit card numbers and financial transactions covered by the Payment Card Industry (PCI) Standard.
Information resources with access to confidential or sensitive data
Information covered by nondisclosure agreements
Any information relating to an identified or identifiable person, or personal data, as defined in the GDPR.
Keywords: Privacy, monitoring, information, private information, confidentiality, integrity, availability, access, incident, breach, data breach, disclosure, collection, subpoena, search warrant
Change History: 05/29/2018: Updated link to European Union Data Protection Regulation.
05/25/2018: Updated to comply with European Union General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR).
05/30/2017: Fixed broken link.
01/09/2015: Policy formatting cleanup (e.g., bolding, spacing).
12/17/2014: Updated contact information, made technical edits related to formatting and hyperlinking of related documents.
04/06/2009: Reviewed for accuracy; no changes made.
10/30/2007: Approved by the Provost and Executive Vice Chancellor.
Information Access & Technology Categories: Privacy & Security
Add new comment
Request Previous Policy Version
Can't Find What You're Looking For?
Let Us Help »
Apply »
One of 34 U.S. public institutions in the prestigious Association of American Universities
Nearly $290 million in financial aid annually
44 nationally ranked graduate programs.
—U.S. News & World Report
Top 50 nationwide for size of library collection.
—ALA
23rd nationwide for service to veterans
—"Best for Vets," Military Times
Give to KU »
